<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-10T13:36:56-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">TrEnCh-Ed</title><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><entry><title type="html">Welcome! Learn about TrEnCh education</title><link href="/about" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome! Learn about TrEnCh education" /><published>2020-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/about</id><content type="html" xml:base="/about">&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-trench-ed&quot;&gt;What is TrEnCh-Ed?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TrEnCh-Ed is the educational branch of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trenchproject.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The TrEnCh Project&lt;/a&gt;, which builds computational and visualization tools to &lt;b&gt;Tr&lt;/b&gt;anslate &lt;b&gt;En&lt;/b&gt;vironmental &lt;b&gt;Ch&lt;/b&gt;ange into organismal responses. We created this website as a tutorial on the science behind those tools for people who are interested in learning about how living things on our planet are responding to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TrEnCh and TrEnCh-Ed are productions of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.washington.edu/lbuckley/&quot;&gt;Buckley Lab&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Washington, Seattle, and are funded by NSF DBI#1349865 (“CAREER: Computational and visualization tools for translating climate change into ecological impacts”).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/MELSAN.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-use-the-site&quot;&gt;How to use the site&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The material on this website is written to be easily accessible to advanced high schoolers, beginning undergraduates, and beyond. If you are an educator, we invite you to integrate TrEnCh-Ed into your classroom or homework activities in any way that works for you. Alignments between our content and Next Generation Science Standards is available in the &lt;a href=&quot;/resources&quot;&gt;teacher’s guide&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;a href=&quot;/resources&quot;&gt;resource page&lt;/a&gt; also included worksheets for high school and undergraduate students. The best way to approach the site is to move from left to right along the tabs on the home page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with our basic introduction to &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change&quot;&gt;climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand how climate affects the &lt;a href=&quot;/physiology&quot;&gt;physiology&lt;/a&gt; of living things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Find out why ecologists use elevational and latitudinal &lt;a href=&quot;/gradients&quot;&gt;gradients&lt;/a&gt; and sources of &lt;a href=&quot;/history&quot;&gt;historical data&lt;/a&gt; to help predict the biological impacts of climate change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apply your new knowledge by exploring the &lt;a href=&quot;/RShiny&quot;&gt;data visualization apps&lt;/a&gt; we built to dive deep into four case studies about climate change and organismal responses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;a href=&quot;/resources&quot;&gt;glossary and resources&lt;/a&gt; as needed to understand technical terms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meet-the-scientists-and-trench-ed-team&quot;&gt;Meet the Scientists and TrEnCh-Ed team&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/scientist_profiles&quot;&gt;Learn more about the scientists who collected the data used in the visualizations!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://uwpcc.ocean.washington.edu/person/Miriam_Bertram&quot;&gt;Miriam Bertram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is the Assistant Director for the Program on Climate Change at the University of Washington and often works with educators and scientists to collaborate around classroom content development.  She is co-editor of an open access teaching resource “Climate Science for the Classroom” which you can preview &lt;a href=&quot;https://uw.pressbooks.pub/climate/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Miriam periodically teaches cross-disciplinary undergraduate climate courses and will be facilitating two Current Climate Change Workshops for educators at UW Seattle in 2020. She works with TrEnCh-Ed on climate science content and organizing workshops to introduce high school teachers to TrEnCh-Ed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://faculty.washington.edu/lbuckley/&quot;&gt;Lauren Buckley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a Professor in the UW Department of Biology who leads the TrEnCh project. Her research aims to improve forecasts of ecological and evolutionary responses to climate change and focuses on montane butterflies and grasshoppers. She teaches courses in Climate Change Biology and Physiological Ecology and Evolution. &lt;a href=&quot;/scientist_profiles&quot;&gt;Learn more about Lauren in her Scientist Profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meeraleesethi.com/&quot;&gt;Meera Lee Sethi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a graduate student in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://faculty.washington.edu/jhrl/Index.html&quot;&gt;Hille Ris Lambers lab&lt;/a&gt; in the UW Department of Biology. She studies climate change and plant-insect interactions. She applied her background in science writing to write the Trench-Ed text. &lt;a href=&quot;/scientist_profiles&quot;&gt;Learn more about Meera in her Scientist Profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.avmey.com/&quot;&gt;Abigail Meyer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a research analyst in the Department of Biology at the University of Washington working on the TrEnCh project. She works at the intersection of computer science and environmental research. She is passionate about climate change, ecology, and education. Abby works on the TrEnCh-Ed content and website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.google.com/site/ellijtheobald/&quot;&gt;Elli Theobald&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is an Assistant Teaching Professor in the department of Biology at the University of Washington. Her research focuses on teaching practices that promote equity and inclusion in college classrooms. She teaches the large introductory biology course focused on Evolution and Ecology as well as an upper division course in the biological impacts of climate change. Elli works to align TrEnCh-Ed with teaching standards and best practices and to develop content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nicholas (Nick) Verbanic&lt;/strong&gt; is a chemistry and AP Environmental Science teacher at Lake Washington High School in Kirkland, WA. He is a recent graduate of the Master in Instructional Leadership program at the University of Washington where he researched the equitable implementation of Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS) in a high school chemistry professional learning community. He is working with TrEnCh-Ed to help teachers see how climate science is in the Next Generation Science Standards so they can help educate future generations of scientists. He led the development of teacher guides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://education.uw.edu/people/faculty/mwind&quot;&gt;Mark Windschitl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is a faculty member in the College of Education at the University of Washington. He studies the use of ambitious teaching practices in classrooms and how students learn about complex phenomena.  He is assisting in envisioning the TrEnCh-Ed curriculum and designing workshops to introduce high school teachers to TrEnCh-Ed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Macy Zwanzig&lt;/strong&gt; is a life sciences teacher at Redmond High School. She has been working with TrEnCh-Ed to apply her knowledge of climate science and life sciences as they relate to NGSS and AP Environmental Science standards to develop some useful tools for teachers to take back to their classrooms.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">What is TrEnCh-Ed?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/bg.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/bg.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate Change</title><link href="/climate" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate Change" /><published>2020-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-11T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/climate</id><content type="html" xml:base="/climate">&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-climate-and-how-is-it-changing&quot;&gt;What is Climate, and How is it Changing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark Twain is often credited with one of the most intuitive and accurate descriptions of the difference between weather and climate you are likely to encounter. He said: “Climate is what you expect; weather is what you get.” Weather is the name we give to specific atmospheric conditions occurring at a specific place and time: It was sunny and warm in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, on the afternoon of June 19, 1995. Climate is what we call the general conditions we see over a long period, usually on a larger spatial scale: Malaysia has a tropical climate that is hot and humid with abundant rainfall throughout the year. You can think of climate as a running average of weather records in which day to day fluctuations—like an unusually warm December weekend in Chicago—are evened out, and broad patterns—like frigid, snowy winters in the Midwest—become obvious. For this reason, when we talk about climate change, what we’re referring to is a pattern of significant, long-term changes that are taking place on the scale of the entire globe. You can explore some of these changes in the interactive linked below, produced by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.nasa.gov&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;NASA Climate Change website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://climate.nasa.gov/interactives/climate_time_machine&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;700&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the biggest changes we’re seeing are in global temperatures. As a result of huge increases in carbon emissions, average global temperatures have risen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.giss.nasa.gov/research/news/20180118/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a little over 1° C&lt;/a&gt; (or about 2° F) since preindustrial times, and climate change-induced warming is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ipcc.ch/reports&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;projected to continue&lt;/a&gt; throughout the rest of the 21st century and beyond. However, climate is multi-faceted, and many other aspects of it are also changing. The increased carbon dioxide in our atmosphere that drives warming contributes to ocean acidification, since carbon dioxide that dissolves into water turns into carbonic acid. And higher temperatures increase evaporation, which means more water is moved from the earth into the atmosphere. This water vapor is then carried off on air currents, bringing more precipitation to places that are already prone to it (storms may occur less frequently but be much larger). In other places droughts will become more common, and humidity levels will change as well. These changes will have major effects on water availability for both people and agriculture, and may make once-extreme events like flooding routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the wind is affected by climate change. Winds are produced when air currents of different temperatures meet. Because air temperatures are warming more quickly at the earth’s poles than at the equator, these differences are getting smaller, and average global wind speeds are slowing. This illustrates one of the major complexities of climate change, which is that it’s variable: it isn’t taking place at the same rate across space and time. Polar and temperate regions are experiencing more dramatic increases in temperature than the tropics, winters are warming more than summers, and nights are warming more than days. In addition, climate extremes, including events like heat waves and floods due to torrential rain storms, are increasing in frequency and length. Together, all this means that in addition to changes in mean climate conditions, the range of climate conditions a species experiences may expand or contract, and it may be more likely to be exposed to extreme conditions.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">What is Climate, and How is it Changing?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/climate.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/climate.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Physiology</title><link href="/physiology" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Physiology" /><published>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/physiology</id><content type="html" xml:base="/physiology">&lt;h3 id=&quot;temperature-and-physiology-all-curves-all-the-time&quot;&gt;Temperature and Physiology: All Curves, All The Time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does climate affect life on earth? Human beings are pretty special in this regard—we—have developed technologies like air-conditioning and heating to change our environments, we can choose clothing to suit the weather, and many of us can easily travel long distances. Most species aren’t like us, so the environmental conditions where they live have much more of an impact on their activities and function. The specific details of this impact (which conditions are the most important, and what effect they have) depend on that particular organism’s physiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important ideas to understand about how climate affects living things, especially when it comes to ectotherms – organisms whose body temperature is dependent on external heat sources rather than internal physiology–, is that responses are non-linear—meaning that when we graph them, we don’t see a straight line. This is illustrated in the figures below, all of which show body temperature on the x-axis and relative fitness on the y-axis. (More on fitness in the Gradients section, but the basic idea is that high fitness means more offspring, which is good!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img class=&quot;size-medium&quot; src=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3350654/bin/rstb20120005-g1.jpg&quot; width=&quot;465&quot; height=&quot;369&quot; imgalign=&quot;middle&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
Huey et al., 2012
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each curve shows how a hypothetical ectotherm’s fitness changes with its body temperature. Note that since measuring fitness directly requires waiting for an individual to reproduce, we often create curves like these by approximating fitness with some other measure of performance, like locomotion. Part a) shows that above or below a critical minimum and maximum temperature (&lt;em&gt;CTmin&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;CTmax&lt;/em&gt;), the animal has zero fitness—in other words, if it’s too cold or too hot, it can’t move (or presumably reproduce) at all. Its &lt;em&gt;tolerance range&lt;/em&gt; is everything in between. Its &lt;em&gt;performance breadth&lt;/em&gt; is the range of temperatures at which it has relatively high fitness, and &lt;em&gt;To&lt;/em&gt; is its optimal body temperature—the temperature at which it has maximum possible fitness. Part b) helps to demonstrate why it matters so much that this is a curve. Look at the arrow that shows climate warming. If an individual is currently at point A, a few degrees of warming will increase its fitness. But for an individual currently at point B, any warming will be detrimental—it will tip it over the peak of the curve and lower fitness. Parts c) and d) show why climate change may have a bigger impact on “thermal specialists” (organisms with a narrow range of temperature tolerance) than “thermal generalists”; the same amount of change in body temperature results in much bigger changes in fitness in figure c) than figure d).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most useful measures of performance is metabolism (the chemical reactions that sustain life and provide energy), and plotting metabolism against temperature can help us understand why organisms often respond to climate change in non-linear ways. This is because metabolism and temperature have an exponential relationship: metabolism increases more and more rapidly as temperatures increase. As a result, a smaller change in temperature in the tropics, where it’s already hot, can have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature09407&quot;&gt;larger impacts on metabolics&lt;/a&gt;. This relationship can also produce counterintuitive responses to climate change. For instance, warmer winters can be &lt;a href=&quot; https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/brv.12105&quot;&gt;detrimental to overwintering insects&lt;/a&gt; because if their metabolism rates ramp up when they should be in diapause, they quickly deplete their energy resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;move-acclimate-adapt-or-die&quot;&gt;Move, Acclimate, Adapt, or Die&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of climate change, there are four basic ways living things can respond. First, if conditions where an organism lives are no longer suitable, it might move to where the climate is more favorable—a phenomenon known as a range shift. The figures below, for example, illustrate bird species whose distribution ranges are shifting uphill into cooler mountaintops or northward into cooler latitudes. (Species can also “move” in time rather than space, shifting the timing of when certain important life events take place. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/grasshoppers/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;grasshopper&lt;/a&gt; case study on this website illustrates this kind of phenological shift.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://e360.yale.edu/assets/site/_1500x1500_fit_center-center_80/EscalatorToExctinction_Jillian_Ditner_media_web.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;900&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;  
&lt;figcaption&gt;Freeman et al., PNAS 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.borealbirds.org/sites/default/files/Cape-May-Warbler-Range-Shift-web.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; height=&quot;405&quot; align=&quot;center&quot; /&gt;  
&lt;figcaption&gt;Diana Stralberg, Boreal Forest Initiative, 2018&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, living things might stay where they are and acclimate, which is when individual organisms become accustomed to new climatic conditions. For example, the American pika (&lt;em&gt;Ochotona princeps&lt;/em&gt;), a tiny alpine mammal, normally lives exclusively in exposed boulder fields—but as winters in its habitat have warmed, it has changed its behavior. It now seems to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/fee.1502&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;spending more time in coniferous forests and under downed logs&lt;/a&gt;—places where it can escape high temperatures. Other animals have the capacity to become more physiologically tolerant of high temperatures after spending some time experiencing them, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/full/10.1098/rsbl.2007.0408&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Deronectes&lt;/i&gt; diving beetles.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acclimation is a short-term response to environmental changes that is limited to an individual’s lifetime, while adaptation is a longer-term response that involves changes to the genetic makeup of a population. There may be a tradeoff between non-genetic acclimation (also known as plasticity) and genetic adaptation. In the Pacific Ocean there are many species of porcelain crab (in the genus &lt;em&gt;Petrolisthes&lt;/em&gt;) that live in different temperature zones, from cold to hot. Unfortunately, the species that have evolved to be the most tolerant to extremely high temperatures also show the &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/301/5629/65.long&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;least ability to acclimate&lt;/a&gt;, and are the most vulnerable to even small changes in temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/13/PeerJ_-_Petrolisthes_desmarestii.jpg&quot; width=&quot;900&quot; height=&quot;540&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;Petrolisthes desmarestii&lt;/em&gt;, Photo: Wikimedia commons &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of adaptation was discovered after an extreme drought that lasted for years in Southern California—likely linked with climate change. Researchers found that in mustard plants &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/104/4/1278#sec-&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;evolved to produce seeds earlier in the season&lt;/a&gt; so that they now finish their reproductive cycles before the rainy season ends. This is a great example of how multiple responses to climate change can intersect—this mustard species has &lt;em&gt;adapted&lt;/em&gt; in a way that &lt;em&gt;moves&lt;/em&gt; the timing of its reproductive events to match a more favorable climate. Similarly, the butterfly case study on this website illustrates &lt;em&gt;morphological&lt;/em&gt; (physical or structural) changes that are likely the result of both &lt;em&gt;acclimation&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;adaptation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, organisms that fail to respond sufficiently to climate change in other ways may die. Entire species may go extinct either locally (in one location) or globally, or they may experience marked decreases in abundance—the size of a population. The Bramble Cay melomys (&lt;em&gt;Melomys rubicola&lt;/em&gt;), a small rodent that lived on only one island in Australia, is likely one casualty of climate change. While we may never know for sure what resulted in this species &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.nationalgeographic.com/2016/06/first-mammal-extinct-climate-change-bramble-cay-melomys/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;going extinct&lt;/a&gt;, the most probable direct cause is the loss of its habitat, as rising sea levels caused by warming and expanding ocean waters shrank down the available territory on the small island.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-determines-these-outcomes&quot;&gt;What determines these outcomes?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything we’ve talked about so far reveals that: 1) “Climate change” is a complex phenomenon, involving many environmental variables shifting in ways that aren’t uniform across space and time, and 2) Individual species can display a multitude of responses to these impacts. This incredible complexity is the central challenge of predicting how climate change will impact life on earth. Ecologists approach this challenge in several ways, but the one that we’ll focus on here is the use of species traits. A trait is any phenotypic characteristic or feature of an organism (e.g. body size, coloration, diet, etc.). Functional traits are the most useful in terms of making climate change predictions—these are simply traits that are relevant to an organism’s interactions with its environment or its ecological role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case studies on this website, you’ll be able to use real data to test hypotheses about how functional traits affect the way different species or populations respond to changes in climate. One trait that’s likely to have a major impact on climate change responses, for example, is dispersal ability: the extent to which individuals (or their genes) are able to move from one location to another. A young brown bear leaving its mother’s side to seek out its own territory is dispersing; so is a dandelion seed blown miles away by the wind. It’s pretty intuitive that climate change is more likely to result in range shifts for species with relatively high dispersal ability than those with low dispersal ability. (Perhaps less intuitive is that high dispersal ability may result in slower adaptation, if it increases gene flow between populations and causes the loss of rare genes that might be beneficial under a new climate regime. For more, see the “Gradients” section.) Another trait that’s likely to affect outcomes is thermal specialization, described above. Species that are thermal generalists can thrive under a wider range of temperatures than thermal specialists, and are therefore more likely to acclimate, while specialists are more vulnerable to the threat of extinction because they’re sensitive to smaller changes in temperature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ai2-s2-public.s3.amazonaws.com/figures/2017-08-08/6cdf8170d7575e3d1ac3b3a9e69cae09d5abed0b/4-Figure4-1.png&quot; width=&quot;656&quot; height=&quot;536&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;Glenn Tattersall et al., 2012&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, since the data you’ll be exploring all come from montane, or mountain-living, animals, elevational range is an important functional trait. (Elevational differences are also discussed in greater detail in the “Gradients” section.) For instance, since mountain peaks tend to be both narrow and rocky, it’s more difficult for high-elevation populations to move upward to track climate than low-elevation populations. But weather extremes are more common at high elevations, so—surprisingly—these populations may already have the genetic capacity to acclimate to the extreme temperatures climate change is likely to bring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;environmental-vs-organismal-drivers&quot;&gt;Environmental vs. organismal drivers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you work through the case studies, think about how both climate variability (which has to do with the environment) and functional traits (which have to do with organisms) influence species responses to climate change. If you find that a particular population shows a bigger response than others, is it because the climate in its range has changed more? Or is it because one or more of its functional traits make it either more sensitive, or more capable of responding, to climate change? Try to use the available data to tease apart these possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">Temperature and Physiology: All Curves, All The Time</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/MELSAN.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/MELSAN.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gradients</title><link href="/gradients" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gradients" /><published>2020-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/gradients</id><content type="html" xml:base="/gradients">&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-a-gradient&quot;&gt;What is a gradient?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The word gradient comes from the Latin root &lt;em&gt;gradus&lt;/em&gt;, meaning “a step towards, or a step climbed on a ladder or stair.” Biologists are very interested in climatic gradients—places where the environment changes in a measurable and predictable way as you move in a particular direction. For instance, average temperatures gradually fall and average precipitation and wind speeds rise as you travel upwards on an elevational gradient, such as a mountain. Similarly, we see dramatic shifts in climate along latitudinal gradients—lines running between the Earth’s north and south poles—with equatorial locations being much warmer and having much longer growing seasons than those closer to the poles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be difficult, time consuming, and expensive to conduct laboratory experiments that directly manipulate climatic variables and test how organisms respond. That’s why natural gradients are so valuable. Observing species where they naturally occur at different locations along a climatic gradient provides insight into how their distributions, behavior, physiology, or genetics are affected by environmental conditions. To do this, biologists often set up an elevational or latitudinal transect—a series of study sites located at approximately equal distances apart along a gradient. Data collected from a transect can then be used to try to predict how organisms will respond to future climate change. In fact, this is often called a “space for time substitution” approach, because instead of conducting a study that stretches out for a long period of time, we can conduct one that stretches out over a large space, and by doing so allows us to “look into the future.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if we find that the abundance of various plant species is different at different sites on a transect, that suggests something about the ideal environmental conditions for each species, as well as the limits of the conditions it can tolerate. If conditions change, one thing species might do is shift their geographical distribution to track, or follow, their ideal climate. By comparing climate data with species abundance data, we can build a statistical model that predicts where each species will be distributed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/7/70/Altitudinal_zones_of_Alps_mountains-extended_diagram.svg/600px-Altitudinal_zones_of_Alps_mountains-extended_diagram.svg.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
Different zones on a mountain are home to different vegetation types. Image: Wikimedia&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ecology-and-evolution-along-gradients&quot;&gt;Ecology and evolution along gradients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case studies on this website involve data collected on invertebrates living along both elevational and latitudinal gradients: grasshoppers in Colorado and butterflies in Colorado, Wyoming, Montana, and the Canadian Rocky Mountains. It’s worth taking a moment to consider several characteristics that are common to the ecology and evolution of species living along environmental gradients. Remember that gradients are directional; that is, conditions don’t change randomly as you move along them, but tend to increase or decrease continuously. Therefore, opposite ends of a gradient are: 1) extremely different from each other, and 2) where we find relatively extreme environmental conditions. For this reason, we often see different fitness constraints affecting individuals living at opposite ends of a gradient. (Biologically, fitness refers to the ability of an organism to reproduce and pass on its genes to the next generation, and since no individual can have an infinite number of offspring, a constraint is anything that limits this ability.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At low elevations on a mountain, for example, where daily temperatures are the warmest and the growing season is the longest, competition with other species for food and other resources may place the strongest constraint on fitness. In contrast, insufficient warmth and a very short season for growth and reproduction may be the biggest fitness constraints at high elevations. These differences affect how these populations evolve, because natural selection will favor different traits for each population— at low elevations, individuals that are better competitors will pass on more of their genes, while at high elevations, the same will be true of individuals that require the least resources to reproduce. For example, the same species of alpine plant may produce larger flowers in lower elevation meadows, because showy blooms attract pollinators away from competing plants. In meadows located at the highest elevations, smaller flowers may be more favorable because they can develop more quickly, and be pollinated in time for fruit and seeds to mature before the season ends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these phenotypic differences are the result of evolutionary change, meaning they come from differences in genetics, we describe these populations as being locally adapted. That is, the effects of natural selection have led to them becoming more well-suited to the specific (local) environmental conditions where they are found. You might imagine that any population experiencing a specific set of pressures from natural selection should eventually become locally adapted, but this can only happen if gene flow among populations is limited. Gene flow occurs whenever individuals, or the genes they carry, move between populations—like an adult butterfly laying eggs at a different location from where it emerged as a caterpillar, or a seed being blown on the wind to a different location from where its parent plant was rooted. When new genes arrive in a population, they change its genetic makeup. This can be beneficial; greater genetic variation contributes to the population’s ability to adapt to future changes, by increasing the chances that it holds alleles coding for traits that are suitable for different conditions. However, genes flowing in from elsewhere can also “drown out” those of local inhabitants, making it less likely for local adaptation to occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Differences among populations along a gradient can also be due to plasticity rather than genetic changes. Plasticity refers to organisms with the same genetic makeup displaying different phenotypes depending on the environment in which they live; this name comes from the idea that plastic substances can be molded into many different shapes. Often, the conditions an individual is exposed to as it is maturing (e.g. from an egg to a larva or a larva to an adult) can influence the way its phenotype develops. We call this developmental plasticity. Individuals that are highly plastic can respond well to short-term environmental changes, but these responses cannot then be passed down to their offspring. (In general, high-elevation populations of a species tend to be more plastic than low-elevation populations, to allow them to survive and reproduce in the more variable conditions that occur near mountain peaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure below shows how we can tell the difference between adaptation and plasticity using a reciprocal transplant: an experiment where individuals of the same species from two populations (e.g. cold vs. warm habitats) are collected from the field and then transplanted into the opposite habitat. If the differences between them are due to adaptation, we would expect the transplanted individuals to behave the same as they do in their home location, but if the differences are due to plasticity, we expect to see a shift to the opposite phenotype once they’re transplanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;assets/img/Reciptransplant.jpeg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
Hypothetical results from a reciprocal transplant experiment, image: Buckley lab &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coping-with-climate-change&quot;&gt;Coping with climate change&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The history of gene flow and local adaptation in a given population, as well as its degree of phenotypic plasticity, will all affect its ability to thrive under new conditions. That’s because these forces interact in complex ways to determine how a species living along an environmental gradient will respond to climate change. For example, plasticity can allow individuals to survive under less than optimal conditions, but slow down the process of adaptation to these new conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers led by ecologist Lauren Buckley and Joseph Ehrenberger investigated the impact of behavioral plasticity in a North American lizard species (Yes, behaviors are phenotypic traits!). In this case, what is “plastic” is how these Eastern Fence Lizards behave in response to changes in temperature. Instead of allowing their body temperatures to be dictated by their surroundings, they shuttle between sunny and shady areas all day, keeping their internal body temperatures relatively constant. This strategy is known as behavioral thermoregulation. Thermoregulation is very important for these lizards, because temperature has such a powerful influence on physiological functions like metabolism in ectotherms. But it may ultimately leave them more vulnerable to climate change. Key here is the idea that because behavioral plasticity currently allows most lizards to survive and reproduce under a range of conditions, there isn’t strong selection for lizards whose genes make them more robust against extremely high temperatures. And we know that extreme temperature spikes are going to become much more common in the future. When that happens, these lizards’ reliance on plasticity may ultimately mean they haven’t adapted fast enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: flex; justify-content: center;&quot;&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://live.staticflickr.com/4309/36228164446_22de4915e5_c.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    Eastern Fence Lizard (&lt;em&gt;Sceloporus undulatus&lt;/em&gt;), photo by Mary Keim&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">What is a gradient?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/cropped-web6-1024x256.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/cropped-web6-1024x256.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Historical Data</title><link href="/history" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Historical Data" /><published>2020-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/history</id><content type="html" xml:base="/history">&lt;h3 id=&quot;looking-to-the-past-for-answers&quot;&gt;Looking to the past for answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A major challenge in trying to figure out how living things will respond to changes in our climate that are happening over time is… time itself. Although climate change is actually happening &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-018-07586-5&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;faster than we had expected&lt;/a&gt;, it still takes many years of observations before we can begin to see long-term patterns in biological responses. That’s why, although most scientists didn’t begin to seriously sound the alarm about climate change until the 1980s, the case studies on this website rely on data recorded decades earlier. Past scientific studies and museum specimens that were originally collected for other purposes have proven to be incredibly useful for understanding both how life on earth has already changed with climate, as well as what the future holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason historical records are so valuable is that they help to address the problem of shifting baselines. Fisheries scientist named Daniel Pauly first used this term in 1995 to describe how our ideas about what is “normal” or “extreme” (i.e. our “baselines”) shift unconsciously over time as our experiences change. One &lt;a href=&quot;https://peerj.com/articles/6395/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;clever study &lt;/a&gt;searched newspaper headlines published between 1869 and 2015, pulling out headlines where a superlative like giant, huge, or monster was used to describe a fish that had been caught. For many overfished species, such as whale sharks, the authors found declines in the lengths of fish that made the headlines—meaning newsworthy fish don’t have to be as big as they used to be. Examining historic datasets is one way to guard against the problem of shifting baselines, because it gives us information about how things have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-repeat-the-same-study&quot;&gt;Why repeat the same study?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most extraordinary examples of research using historical datasets involves the diaries of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.elsevier.com/connect/tracking-climate-change-with-the-help-of-henry-david-thoreau&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;19th-century American environmentalist and writer Henry David Thoreau&lt;/a&gt;, who lived in Concord, Massachusetts. Thoreau was passionate about nature, and between 1851 and 1858 he recorded his observations about 300 different species of plants and birds, including the first dates each season on which he saw trees leafing out, flowers blooming, and migratory birds arriving to breed. Biologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rprimacklab.com/&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;Richard Primack&lt;/a&gt; saw the opportunity for a resurvey, a repeat study of the same species in the same area to track changes over time. By combining the tables in Thoreau’s diaries with temperature data from a nearby observatory and his own contemporary observations, a team led by Primack determined that spring temperatures in Concord had warmed by an average of 5°C, and over the same period wildflowers had shifted the phenology of their first flowering dates by an average of ten days. Not only does this kind of work allow us to quantify the amount of change that has already taken place, it also provides a (rough) estimate of how things will change in the future. In this case, we can predict that on average, every 1°C of warming will result in the first appearance of flowers Concord occurring an average of two days earlier. You can explore some of the Concord wildflower data in our &lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/PlantPhenology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Plant Phenology data visualization.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.elsevier.com/__data/assets/image/0020/32366/Figure-1.png&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The relationship between spring temperatures and first-flowering date, from Ellwood et al. 2013, PLoS ONE doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0053788. Each data point represents a year of pre-2010 phenology data averaged across species. Mean phenology and 95% prediction intervals are also depicted for 2010 (green) and 2012 (red). Species include 1) serviceberry (Amelanchier canadensis), 2) marsh marigold (Caltha palustris), 3) pink lady slipper (Cypripedium acaule), 4) rhodora (Rhododendron canadense), 5) nodding trillium (Trillium cernuum), and 6) highbush blueberry (Vaccinium corymbosum). &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another famous resurvey project is currently being conducted at the University of California, Berkeley. Researchers at the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology are revisiting hundreds of sites that were originally surveyed between 1904 and 1940 by Joseph Grinnell, the founding director of the museum, and his expedition partner and paleontological collector Annie Montague Alexander. Grinnell and Alexander wanted to document bird and mammal diversity across California because they were interested in biological responses to changing land use. A century later, scientists and students launched &lt;a href=&quot;http://mvz.berkeley.edu/Grinnell/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Grinnell Resurvey Project&lt;/a&gt; to retrace their footsteps and discover how these species have responded to the effects of climate change in the intervening years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-value-of-museum-specimens&quot;&gt;The value of museum specimens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physical museum collections—preserved specimens, like pressed plants, pinned insects, and bird skins—can be even more exciting sources of historic information than written records. This is because we can often extract additional biological data from these specimens. For example, measurements of museum specimens of &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs10682-017-9917-0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two species of North American mice&lt;/a&gt; showed that as winters in Southern Quebec warmed, both species experienced changes in skull shape and tooth positioning, which may be related to shifts in their diet caused by changes in vegetation. And in one of the case studies on this website, museum specimens of butterflies were used to measure shifts in wing coloration that occurred with climate change. The development of new technologies that didn’t even exist at the time when some specimens were collected can also increase their scientific value tremendously, including DNA sequencing and other biochemical analyses.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">Looking to the past for answers</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/butterfliesindrawer.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/butterfliesindrawer.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Data Visualizations</title><link href="/RShiny" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data Visualizations" /><published>2020-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/RShiny</id><content type="html" xml:base="/RShiny">&lt;p&gt;We built these interactive data visualization apps using RShiny to allow you to form hypotheses about biological responses to climate change and test them using data. One thing we love about these examples is that they take advantage of both climatic gradients &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; historical data to really help us understand and predict the effects of climate change. Each case study includes all the background you need to understand the data and an interactive interface you can use to visualize it in different ways. Worksheets with additional background and questions designed to promote inquiry-based learning are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;resources page&lt;/a&gt;. The visualizations listed below start with organismal level responses to climate change and proceed to population level responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://map.trenchproject.com/Climate-Change-Metabolism/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Metabolic Impacts of Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use historic climate data and the temperature dependence of metabolism to compare climate impacts between temperate and tropical regions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/RShiny_ButterflyHeatBudget/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Energy Budgets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Using a heat budget model to estimate an organism’s body temperature due to their environment and morphology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/ClimateBiology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robomussels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use data from biomimetic temperature sensors to explore how organisms experience climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/butterflies/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Butterfly Museum Specimens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use data from museum specimens to explore how temperature influences morphology and phenology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/PlantPhenology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wildflower Phenology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use historical and resurvey data to explore how temperature influences phenology. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/RShiny_RMBL-phenology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RMBL Phenology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use climate and phenological data from Rock Mountain Biological Laboratory to explore migration and overwintering species in a high-elevation ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/grasshoppers/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Grasshopper Resurvey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use historical and resurvey data to explore how temperature influences developmental rates and phenology. Also, meet one of the scientists behind this project &lt;a href=&quot;https://trench-ed.github.io/#cesar&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://huckley.shinyapps.io/RShiny_RangeShifts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Marine Range Shifts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/b&gt;: Use survey data to explore the range shifting of marine populations in response to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">We built these interactive data visualization apps using RShiny to allow you to form hypotheses about biological responses to climate change and test them using data. One thing we love about these examples is that they take advantage of both climatic gradients and historical data to really help us understand and predict the effects of climate change. Each case study includes all the background you need to understand the data and an interactive interface you can use to visualize it in different ways. Worksheets with additional background and questions designed to promote inquiry-based learning are available on the resources page. The visualizations listed below start with organismal level responses to climate change and proceed to population level responses.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/graph.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="/graph.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Resources</title><link href="/resources" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Resources" /><published>2020-01-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="/resources">&lt;h3 id=&quot;teacher-guide-hs&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1P-OzJkg_wltSPH69YIPgveceSWw4bAkQ/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Teacher Guide (HS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teacher-guide-college&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1aArVGZvIAD_Ml2IyqbGB05VevDLL5UUw/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Teacher Guide (College)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This teacher guide will provide you with a better understanding as to how the tools of the TrEnCh-Ed program are organized and how they can be potentially used in your classroom. These tools can be used in teaching the high school Next Generation Science Standards (NGSS), the Advanced Placement (AP) Environmental Science course, and introductory climate science and ecology college courses. The tools are also designed to align with the AAAS Vision and Change in Undergraduate Biology Education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The worksheets contain additional background and questions to facilitate inquiry-based learning. We additionally include a &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/u/2/folders/1Bb6Sx3z5e_M8hapC1BK3G8bhy7pIjxVM&quot;&gt;folder&lt;/a&gt; with resources for teaching the basics of climate science as background for the TrEnCh-Ed activities. &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/RiZNitsLTAccgghT6&quot;&gt;Fill out this request form&lt;/a&gt; with information about your educational role to access the answer keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;worksheets-hs--and-college-level&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1-y3DQW5DGSsuJGUquDbcdnn15mr3jMZL?usp=sharing&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;Worksheets (HS- and College-level)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;answer-keys-hs--and-college-level&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jstrieb.github.io/link-lock/#eyJ2IjoiMC4wLjEiLCJlIjoicjNXSWRRQTcwSlJnWUFIL2VBQXV6Vk5TTWpJTVN6MXFiV0E0c1l6VTVEOGQvdmFNZWFpY1YvbGYxc2JMSEp3WkkxQ2hZQ3VHajRicTJuaVY3ejVnU255eHhXRS95RUorbnhjRGxsUjlrbnRSQXhrUU5iNnAzOGtQdzFDcW1taldNWVNyVlE9PSIsImkiOiJyemVxNUd2SlRJN3RZSTZ6In0=&quot;&gt;Answer Keys (HS- and College-level)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Educators interested in helping us better these resources are encouraged to fill out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://forms.gle/FsUoBG7fHtDTUdoa6&quot;&gt;feedback form&lt;/a&gt; of TrEnCh-Ed. As well, we have created a &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/drive/folders/1tslkxfLG4VgAW41Zf3lxdxkE6RpeHzgX?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;folder to collect any edits&lt;/a&gt; you make to the materials we provide to help us continue to improve TrEnCh-Ed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;glossary&quot;&gt;Glossary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quizlet.com/_8lewtg?x=1jqt&amp;amp;i=2zu0qr&quot;&gt;Quizlet study set&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Acclimation&lt;/strong&gt;: An individual level (generally non-genetic) physiological or behavioral response to a change in the environment that enables the individual to cope with this change (e.g. a plant growing deeper roots (to access moisture deeper in the soil) in response to a drought). See also: “&lt;strong&gt;Plasticity&lt;/strong&gt;”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptation&lt;/strong&gt;: A change in the genetic makeup of a population as a result of natural selection in which a beneficial trait becomes more common (e.g. male birds developing colorful feathers because this increases their success in mating).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allele&lt;/strong&gt;: A specific version of a gene.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amplitude&lt;/strong&gt;: The degree of difference from an average (e.g. the extent of variability in temperature from the mean)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biomimetic&lt;/strong&gt;: Something that mimics or is inspired by a biological process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Climatic Gradient&lt;/strong&gt;: A directional change in climate (e.g. temperature, precipitation) along a geographic axis (e.g. a fall in temperature with increasing elevation on a mountain, an increase in precipitation with decreasing latitude).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical Thermal Minimum/Maximum&lt;/strong&gt;: The minimum and maximum temperatures at which an organism can function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diapause&lt;/strong&gt;: A period during which an organism is dormant and development is paused, usually seen in invertebrates.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dispersal&lt;/strong&gt;: The movement of an individual or a propagule (seed, spore) across space, leading to gene flow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distribution Range&lt;/strong&gt;: The geographic area in which a species or population can be found.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ectotherm&lt;/strong&gt;: An organism whose body temperature is dependent on external heat sources rather than internal physiology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elevational Transect&lt;/strong&gt;: A series of sites located along an elevational gradient, at which scientific observations are made.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness&lt;/strong&gt;: The number of offspring an individual or population produces which go on to successfully breed themselves.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fitness Constraint&lt;/strong&gt;: Any factor that limits the fitness of an individual or population (e.g. a limited number of mates; limited food resources; environmental stress).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequency&lt;/strong&gt;: The rate at which something occurs or is repeated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gene&lt;/strong&gt;: A sequence of nucleotides in a fixed location on a chromosome that encodes (contains instructions to make) a protein that performs a particular function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gene Flow&lt;/strong&gt;: The movement of alleles between populations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genotype&lt;/strong&gt;: The genetic makeup of an individual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instar&lt;/strong&gt;: A phase in the development of an invertebrate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Adaptation&lt;/strong&gt;: The process by which a population becomes more genetically well-suited to the specific environmental conditions where it is found, as a result of limited gene flow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metabolism&lt;/strong&gt;: The chemical processes taking place inside an organism that maintain life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Morphology&lt;/strong&gt;: The physical form and structure of a living thing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Natural Selection&lt;/strong&gt;: The process by which alleles encoding for traits that increase fitness become more common and alleles encoding for traits that decrease fitness become less common.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phenology&lt;/strong&gt;: The timing of important events in the life of an organism.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phenotype&lt;/strong&gt;: The set of observable traits belonging to an individual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physiology&lt;/strong&gt;: The physical and chemical functions and activity of living things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plasticity&lt;/strong&gt;: The ability of an individual to change its phenotype in response to the environment without changing its genotype. See also: “&lt;strong&gt;Acclimation&lt;/strong&gt;”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Range Shift&lt;/strong&gt;: A change in the geographic area in which a species of population can be found.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sedentary&lt;/strong&gt;: Of an animal, meaning that it lives in the same place throughout its life. For example, a mussel attached to a rock.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Space-For-Time Substitution&lt;/strong&gt;: An ecological technique by which sites that are separated in space are used as analogues for sites that are separated in time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thermal Generalist/Specialist&lt;/strong&gt;: An organism that is capable of functioning at a wide range of temperatures vs. one that can only function within a narrow temperature window.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thermoregulation&lt;/strong&gt;: The process by which an organism maintains its preferred body temperature, either through internal physiological processes or behavioral changes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trait&lt;/strong&gt;: Any characteristic of an organism (e.g. coat color); a functional trait is one that is important in determining an organism’s ecology or evolution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Paul Le and Abigail Meyer</name></author><summary type="html">Teacher Guide (HS)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="/chalkboard.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="/chalkboard.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>